# JONATHAN VARGAS

Analyst, Developer, Penetration Tester.

San Antonio, TX

11jonathanvargas11@gmail.com

(210) 550-6119

Senior undergraduate at the University of Texas at San Antonio majoring in Cyber Security and Information Systems. I am enthusiastic about hardening operating systems and network security and strive to lead the next generation of cyber security professionals. My goal is to find opportunities to apply my diligently-learned principles of security with a team that encourages innovation and leadership.

I have authored various penetration testing methodology articles on my website, organized a cyber security CTF competition for two ethical hacking online communities, and acquired industry IT experience during my undergraduate studies through two internships and one contract opportunity. Through extracurricular activities, I have consulted with leaders in my field on security practices and headed an on-campus organization with weekly lessons.

I am motivated by a deep desire to develop secure networks and ensure our private data remains private.



#### WORK EXPERIENCE -----

#### **Cyber Security CTF Organizer**

**Self** - San Antonio, TX August 2020 to Present

- Executed an open capture-the-flag competition for members of the Try Hack Me and Hack The Box ethical hacking communities. Two teams of five members were tasked with exploiting a remote server, gaining access, then establishing tighter security controls in order for the opposing team to fail at breaching entry.
- Assembled a collection of three exploitable machines containing vulnerabilities in line with the Open Web Application Security Project's (OWASP) top ten security risks.
- Researched real-world security compromising incidents and integrated recent exploits into the competition's vulnerable machines.

#### **SQL** Developer

WARD NORTH AMERICAN - San Antonio, TX

February 2020 to August 2020

- Optimize MS SQL reporting scripts for lower data retrieval latency.
- Debug live SQL reports for misreported values.
- Collaborate with various department managers to build new tables and reports that fit the department's requirements.
- Write over 5,000 lines of code monthly to adjust for the company's changing data management practices.

### **President**

 $\textbf{UTSA Swing Dance Society} \cdot \textbf{San Antonio}, \, \textbf{TX}$ 

May 2019 to May 2020

- Headed a student-led organization to preserve the social dance and culture of the swing jazz era
- Orchestrated weekly dance instruction

- · Cultivated a Board of Executives
- Partnered with community and intercollegiate organizations

#### **IT Intern**

WARD NORTH AMERICAN - San Antonio, TX

March 2019 to February 2020

- Spearheaded the development of aggregation software to understand sales trends
- Developed two complex SQL and JDBC algorithms to fully automate corporate budget analysis
- Inspired the prototyping of Ward University: a learning management system for small corporations.
- Collaborated closely with cloud service provider to ensure network reliability.
- Offered expert IT troubleshooting and consultation for software and hardware solutions.
- · Gained experience using Wireshark to monitor network activity and identify network issues.
- Developed automated emails to be sent out to customers and agents.

### **Cyber Security Intern**

Alamo City Engineering Services - San Antonio, TX

July 2017 to March 2018

- Acquired industry hands-on open source intelligence experience through utilizing deep web data crawling APIs.
- Collaborated with a team to delegate tasks and develop strategies to implement information system automation software.

#### **Fire Marshal Intern**

Bexar County Fire Marshal's Office - San Antonio, TX

May 2016 to August 2016

- Gained experience of professionalism present in a standard business environment
- Assisted in fire safety inspections by demonstrating knowledge of fire safety standards.
- Provided administrative assistance during the investigative process



# **EDUCATION**

### **Bachelor's in Cyber Security**

**University of Texas at San Antonio** - San Antonio, TX August 2017 to Present

### **Bachelor's in Information Systems**

**University of Texas at San Antonio** - San Antonio, TX August 2017 to Present



SKILLS

- SQL Server
- · Java (3 years)
- Python (2 years)
- · Penetration Testing (1 year)

- · Wireshark (2 years)
- Burp Suite (1 year)
- Operating Systems (2 years)
- · Network Mapping (1 year)
- System Administration (2 years)
- Web Development (3 years)
- Information Security (4 years)
- · Network Security (4 years)
- Encryption (1 year)
- UNIX (1 year)
- Azure (1 year)
- PowerShell (1 year)
- Shell Scripting (2 years)
- pfSense (1 year)
- Security Assessment (1 year)
- MySQL
- · Help Desk (2 years)
- · Cryptography (1 year)



http://vargasportfolio.github.io



### **CERTIFICATIONS AND LICENSES**

### CompTIA Security+

August 2020 to August 2023

By obtaining this certification, I have demonstrated skills necessary to perform core security functions required of any cybersecurity role. I understand how to identify and address potential threats, attacks and vulnerabilities and I have established techniques in risk management, risk mitigation, threat management and intrusion detection.



### **UTSA Swing Dance Society**

August 2018 to Present

President - May 2019 to May 2020

- · Headed a student-led organization to preserve the social dance and culture of the swing jazz era
- Orchestrated weekly dance instruction

- Cultivated a Board of Executives
- Partnered with community organizations.

# **UTSA Computer Security Association**

August 2020 to Present

- Attended weekly discussions on current vulnerabilities, automation tools, and information security principles.
- Visited online workshops for further developing cyber security skills such as risk mitigation, executing security assessments for real world companies, and security hardening tools.
- Consulted with higher-experienced members of my field to explore industry standards and practices.